<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Minimal TEI encoding of page 101 of Shakespeare's First Folio (Bodleian Arch. G
               c.7)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2763-0056">Katarzyna Anna
               Kapitan</distributor>
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-10-16"/>
            <availability>
               <licence>This file is available under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 icence: <ref
                     type="url" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en"
                     >https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en</ref>.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>The Bodleian First Folio: A digital facsimile of the First Folio of
                  Shakespeare's plays, <idno>Bodleian Arch. G c.7.</idno></title>
               <ref type="url" target="http://firstfolio.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/"
                  >http://firstfolio.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/</ref>
               <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
               <availability>
                  <licence>The images and text of the First Folio are released under a Creative
                     Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0) licence.</licence>
               </availability>
               <date/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p> This file has been created by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2763-0056"
               >Katarzyna Anna Kapitan</persName> on <date>16 October 2024</date> for the course
               <title>Modelling humanities data with TEI-XML: Scholarly editing and manuscript
               cataloguing in the digital age</title> at <orgName
               ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q273570">École nationale des chartes -
               PSL</orgName> in <placeName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q90"
            >Paris</placeName>. The transcription uses the materials published on <title>The
               Bodleian First Folio: A digital facsimile of the First Folio of Shakespeare's
               plays</title>, <ref type="url" target="http://firstfolio.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/"
               >http://firstfolio.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/</ref>.</p>
         <p>The file contains a transcription of page 101, where a new play <title>Much Ado About
               Nothing</title> begins. The transcription has been divided into Acts and Scenes, as
            well as columns reflecting the layout of the page. </p>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="low">
               <p>The text has not been corrected.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-10-22">Proofread by <persName
               ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2763-0056">KAK</persName>.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="101"/>
            <head>Much adoe about Nothing.</head>
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <div type="act" n="1">
                  <head>Actus primus, Scena prima.</head>
                  <p>
                     <cb n="1"/> Leonato. Enter Leonato Gouernour of Messina, Innogen his wife, He
                     ro his daughter, and Beatrice his Neece, with a messenger. I Learne in this
                     Letter, that Don Peter of Arra gon, comes this night to Messina. Mess. He is
                     very neere by this: he was not three Leagues off when I left him. Leon. How
                     many Gentlemen haue you lost in this action? Mess. But few of any sort, and
                     none of name. Leon. A victorie is twice it selfe, when the atchieuer brings
                     home full numbers: I finde heere, that Don Pe ter hath bestowed much honor on a
                     yong Florentine, cal led Claudio. Mess. Much deseru'd on his part, and equally
                     remem bred by Don Pedro, he hath borne himselfe beyond the promise of his age,
                     doing in the figure of a Lambe, the feats of a Lion, he hath indeede better
                     bettred expecta tion, then you must expect of me to tell you how. Leo. He hath
                     an Vnckle heere in Messina, wil be very much glad of it. Mess. I haue alreadie
                     deliuered him letters, and there appeares much ioy in him, euen so much, that
                     ioy could not shew it selfe modest enough, without a badg of bit ternesse. Leo.
                     Did he breake out into teares? Mess. In great measure. Leo. A kinde ouerflow of
                     kindnesse, there are no fa ces truer, then those that are so wash'd, how much
                     bet ter is it to weepe at ioy, then to ioy at weeping? Bea. I pray you, is
                     Signior Mountanto return'd from the warres, or no? Mess. I know none of that
                     name, Lady, there was none such in the armie of any sort. Leon. What is he that
                     you aske for Neece? Hero. My cousin meanes Signior Benedick of Padua Mess. O
                     he's return'd, and as pleasant as euer he was. Beat. He set vp his bils here in
                     Messina, &amp; challeng'd Cupid at the Flight: and my Vnckles foole reading the
                     Challenge, subscrib'd for Cupid, and challeng'd him at the Burbolt. I pray you,
                     how many hath hee kil'd and eaten in these warres? But how many hath he kil'd?
                     for indeed, I promis'd to eate all of his killing. Leon. 'Faith Neece, you taxe
                     Signior Benedicke too much, but hee'l be meet with you, I doubt it not. Mess.
                     He hath done good seruice Lady in these wars. Beat. You had musty victuall, and
                     he hath holpe to ease it: he's a very valiant Trencher-man, hee hath an
                     excellent stomacke. <cb n="2"/> Mess. And a good souldier too Lady. Beat. And a
                     good souldier to a Lady. But what is he to a Lord? Mess. A Lord to a Lord, a
                     man to a man, stuft with all honourable vertues. Beat. It is so indeed, he is
                     no lesse then a stuft man: but for the stuffing well, we are all mortall. Leon.
                     You must not (sir) mistake my Neece, there is a kind of merry war betwixt
                     Signior Benedick, &amp; her: they neuer meet, but there's a skirmish of wit
                     between them. Bea. Alas, he gets nothing by that. In our last con flict, foure
                     of his fiue wits went halting off, and now is the whole man gouern'd with one:
                     so that if hee haue wit enough to keepe himselfe warme, let him beare it for a
                     difference betweene himselfe and his horse: For it is all the wealth that he
                     hath left, to be knowne a reaso- nable creature. Who is his companion now? He
                     hath euery month a new sworne brother. Mess. [Is't] possible? Beat. Very easily
                     possible: he weares his faith but as the fashion of his hat, it euer changes
                     with yͤ next block. Mess. I see (Lady) the Gentleman is not in your bookes.
                     Bea. No, and he were, I would burne my study. But I pray you, who is his
                     companion? Is there no young squarer now, [...]that will make a voyage with him
                     to the diuell? Mess. He is most in the company of the right noble Claudio.
                     Beat. O Lord, he will hang vpon him like a disease: he is sooner caught then
                     the pestilence, and the taker runs presently mad. God helpe the noble Claudio,
                     if hee haue caught the Benedict, it will cost him a thousand pound ere he be
                     cur'd. Mess. I will hold friends with you Lady. Bea. Do good friend. Leo. You'l
                     ne're run mad Neece. Bea. No, not till a hot Ianuary. Mess. Don Pedro is
                     approach'd. Enter don Pedro, Claudio, Benedicke, Balthasar, and Iohn the
                     bastard. Pedro. Good Signior Leonato, you are come to meet your trouble: the
                     fashion of the world is to auoid cost, and you encounter it. Leon. Neuer came
                     trouble to my house in the likenes of your Grace: for trouble being gone,
                     comfort should remaine: but when you depart from me, sorrow abides, and
                     happinesse takes his leaue. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
